you
Krishnamurti in dialogue with Dr. Alan
W. Anderson. J. Krishnamurti was born in
South India and educated in England. For the past
40 years he has been speaking in the United
States, Europe, India, Australia, and other parts of
the world. From the outset of his life's work,
he repudiated all connections with organized religions
and ideologies and said that his only
concern was to set men absolutely unconditionally free.
He is the author of many books, among them
The Awakening of Intelligence, The Urgency of
Change, Freedom from the Known, and The Flight
of the Eagle. This is one of a series
of dialogues between Krishnamurti and Dr. Alan W. Anderson,
who is professor of religious studies at
San Diego State University where he teaches Indian
and Chinese scriptures and the oracular
tradition. Dr. Anderson, a published poet,
received his degree from Columbia University and
the Union Theological Seminary. He has been
honored with a Distinguished Teaching
Award from the California State Universities.
Mr. Krishnamurti, I was wonderfully overjoyed in
our last conversation. For myself, just as
as one who was trying in listening to you
to learn something of his inwardness, to follow along the
passage that we had made from fear through the
points as we moved until we came to pleasure,
and as we left off we were still talking of
pleasure. And I hope we can begin now to move along.
We were saying, sir, weren't we,
pleasure, enjoyment, delight, and joy and happiness.
And what relationship has pleasure with enjoyment
and with joy, with happiness? Is pleasure happiness?
Is pleasure joy? Is pleasure enjoyment? Or
is pleasure something entirely different from those two?
A. In English we think we make
a distinction between pleasure and joy without necessarily
knowing what we mean. In our use, in
our employment of the words, we will discriminate sometimes.
We think it odd to use the word pleasure
rather than joy when we think that joy is appropriate.
The relation between the word please and pleasure interests
me very much. We will say to a person,
please sit down, and usually
that would be thought of as...
K. Have the pleasure to sit down.
A. Yes. It's not a request.
K. Please yourself to sit down.
A. It's an invitation, not a request.
K. Not quite.
A. Be pleased to sit down.
K. Be pleased to sit down.
A. It's be pleased to be seated.
K. Yes.
K. Like in Italian, French, so on.
A. Right. So within pleasure itself, the
word pleasure, there's the intimation of joy,
intimation of it that is
not strictly reduced to the word.
K. I would like to question
whether pleasure has any relationship with joy.
A. Pleasure.
A. Not in itself, I take it, you mean.
K. Or even beyond the word.
Is there a line or
a continuity of pleasure to joy?
Is there a connecting link?
Because what is pleasure?
I take pleasure in eating, I take pleasure in walking,
I take pleasure in accumulating money,
I take pleasure in a dozen, dozen, dozen things,
sex, hurting people, sadistic instincts, violent.
They are all forms of a pleasure.
I enjoy. I won't use the word enjoy.
I take pleasure in and pursue that pleasure.
One wants to hurt people,
and that gives great pleasure.
One wants to have power.
It doesn't matter whether you cook, or the wife,
or a thousand people, it's the same.
The pleasure in something which is sustained,
nourished, kept going.
And this pleasure, when it is thwarted,
becomes violent, anger, jealousy, fury,
wanting to break,
all kinds of neurotic activities, and so on, so on.
So, what is pleasure, and what
is it that keeps it going?
What is the pursuit of
it, the constant direction of it?
I think, I think, something
in our first or second conversation,
I think it was the first, is intimated here,
when we talked about the built-in necessity
that one observes in a progress
that is never consummated.
It's just nothing but a
termination and then a new start,
but no consummation at all, no totality,
no fulfilment, feeling full is what I mean by that.
Yes, I understand, sir, but
what is it that's called pleasure?
I see something, something which I enjoy,
and I want it, pleasure, pleasure and possession.
Take that simple thing, which the child, the grown-up man,
the priest, they all have
this feeling of pleasure in possession.
A toy, or a house, or possessing knowledge,
or possessing the idea of God,
or the pleasure the dictators have,
the totalitarian brutalities, the pleasure.
What is that pleasure?
To make it very, very simple, what is that pleasure?
Look, sir, what happens?
There is a single tree on the hill,
green meadow, deer,
and there is this single tree standing on the hill.
You see that and you say, how marvellous.
Not verbally, merely you say, how marvellous,
to communicate to somebody,
but when you are by yourself and see that,
it is really astonishingly beautiful.
The whole movement of the earth, the flowers,
the deer, the meadows, the water,
and the single tree with the shadow.
You see that.
It is almost breathtaking.
And you turn away and go away.
Then thought says, how extraordinary that was.
A. Compared with what now is.
K. How extraordinary.
I must have it again.
I must get that same feeling which I had then,
for two seconds or five minutes.
So thought, see what has taken place.
There was immediate response to that beauty,
non-verbal, non-emotional, non-sentimental, non-romantic.
Then thought comes along and says,
how extraordinary, what a delight that was.
And then the memory of it, and the repetition,
the demand, the desire for the repetition.
A. When we go to performances,
this happens with what we call the encore, doesn't it?
K. Encore.
A. And with encores there is a creeping embarrassment,
because with the first reappearance
– well, this is a sign of adulation, praise,
and everybody is happy.
But then of course there is the problem of
how many more encores can be made,
and maybe the last encore is a
signal that we are fed up now,
we don't want any more.
Yes, I understand, I think I am following you.
K. So thought gives nourishment, sustains it,
and gives it a direction to pleasure.
There was no pleasure at the moment of perception
of that tree, the hill,
the shadows, the deer, the water,
the meadow, the whole thing was astonishing.
That was real, non-verbal, non-romantic and so on.
Perception.
It has nothing to do with
me or you, it was there.
Then thought comes along and says, memory of it,
continuing that memory tomorrow,
and the demand for that, and the pursuit of that.
And when I come back to
it tomorrow, it is not the same.
I feel a little bit shocked, a little bit...
I was inspired, now I must
find means of getting again inspired,
therefore I take a drink, women, this or that.
You follow?
A. Oh, yes, yes, yes.
Do you think in the history of culture
the establishment of festivals would be
related to what you are saying?
K. Of course, it is the whole thing, sir.
A. We live for...
In English we have this saying, to live it up.
The rest of the time we are living it down.
K. Down, yes. Mardi Gras, you
know, the whole business of it.
So there it is. I see that.
See what it is, sir.
Pleasure is sustained by thought.
Sexual pleasure, the image, the thinking over it, all that,
and the repetition of it,
and the pleasure of it, and
go on, keep on, keep on, routine.
Now, what a relationship,
what is the place of pleasure or relationship
to the delight of the moment?
Not even a delight, it is something inexpressible.
So is there any relationship between pleasure and enjoyment?
Enjoyment becomes pleasure when thought says,
I have enjoyed it, I must have more of it.
A. It is actually a falling out of joy.
K. Yes, that is it.
You see, sir, so pleasure has no relationship
to ecstasy, to delight, to enjoyment,
or to joy and happiness.
Because pleasure is the movement of thought in direction.
It doesn't matter what direction, but in a direction.
The others have no direction.
Pleasure and enjoyment, you enjoy.
Joy is something you cannot invite,
happiness you cannot invite,
it happens and you don't know
if you are happy at that moment.
It is only the next moment
you say, how marvellous that was.
So, see what takes place.
Can the mind, the brain,
register the beauty of that hill and tree
and the water and the meadows, and end it?
Not say, I want it again.
A. Yes. This would take us back to that,
what you have just said now,
would take us back to that word negation
that we spoke of before.
Because there has to be a moment
when we are about to fall out.
We are about to fall out.
And what you are saying is,
the moment that about to fall out appears,
something must be done.
K. You will see it in a minute, sir.
You will see what extraordinary things take place.
I see pleasure, enjoyment, joy and happiness.
See pleasure has not related to any of that,
the other two, joy and enjoyment.
So thought gives direction and sustains pleasure.
Right. Now, I ask myself, mind asks,
can there be non-interference of thought,
non-interference of thought in pleasure?
I enjoy.
Why should thought come into it at all?
A. There is no reason at all.
K. But it does. A. It does.
Now, the question arises,
how is the mind, the brain,
to stop thought entering into that enjoyment?
路 murderer
Not to interfere.
Therefore they said,
the ancients and the religious people,
control thought.
You follow? Don't let it creep in.
Therefore control it.
A minute it raises its ugly head,
whack it off.
It's like a hydra.
It keeps on growing.
Now,
is it possible
to enjoy,
to take a delight in that lovely scene
and not thought creeping in?
Is this possible?
I'll show you. It is possible,
completely possible,
if you are attentive at that moment,
completely attentive.
You follow, sir?
A. Which has nothing to do with screwing oneself up
with muscular effort to focus in there.
K. Just be wholly there.
When you see the sunset, see it completely.
When you see a beautiful line of a car,
see it.
And don't let this thought begin.
That means at that moment
be supremely attentive, completely,
with your mind, with your body, with your nerves,
with your eyes, ears, everything attentive.
Then thought doesn't come to you at all.
So, pleasure
is related to thought.
And thought in itself
brings about fragmentation,
pleasure and not pleasure.
Therefore, now, after having pleasure,
I must pursue pleasure.
A. It makes a judgement. K. A judgement.
And the feeling of frustration,
anger, violence, you follow?
All that comes when there is the denial of pleasure.
Which is what the religious people have done.
They are very violent people,
because they have said, no pleasure.
A. The irony of this is overwhelming.
In classical thought,
you have that marvellous monument,
the works of St. Thomas Aquinas,
who never tired of saying,
in his examination of thought,
and the recognition of the judgement,
that one must distinguish in order to unite.
And his motive was very different
from what seems to have been read,
because we've managed to distinguish,
but we never see the thing whole,
and get to the uniting, so the uniting is very...
It's terrible.
So that's the whole point, sir.
So, unless the mind understands the nature of thinking,
really, very, very, very deeply,
mere control means nothing.
Personally, I have never controlled a thing.
It may sound rather absurd, but it is a fact.
It's marvellous.
Never.
But I watched it.
The watching is its own discipline and its own action.
Discipline in the sense,
not conformity, not suppression,
not adjusting yourself to a pattern,
but the sense of correctness,
the sense of excellence.
When you see something, why should you control?
Why should you control
when you see a poisonous bottle on the shelf?
You don't control.
You say, that's quite right, don't drink,
you don't touch it.
It's only when I don't read the sign properly,
when I see and I
think that it is a sweet,
then I take it.
But if I read the label,
if I know what it is,
I won't touch it.
There is no control.
A. No, of course not.
It's self-evident.
K. Yes.
I am thinking of that wonderful story in the Gospel
about Peter who, in the storm,
gets out to walk on the water
because he sees his Lord coming on the water
and he is invited to walk on the water
and he actually makes it a few steps.
And then it says he loses faith,
but it seems to me that one could see that
in terms of what you have been saying,
at the point where thought took over,
he started going down.
That was the time when he started going down.
But he was actually...
The reason that I am referring to that
is because I sense in what you are saying
that there is something that supports,
that is a support,
that is not a support
that is fragmented from something else,
but there is an abiding something
which must be sustaining the person.
K. I wouldn't put it that way, sir.
That leaves a door open,
that opens the door to the
idea in you there is God.
A. Yes, I see the trap.
K. In you there is the higher self,
in you there is the Atman, the permanent...
A. Maybe we shouldn't say anything about that.
K. No, we can say this, no.
To see... look what we have done, sir, this morning.
To see appetite, desire,
to see the implication, the structure of pleasure,
and it is no relation to enjoyment and to joy,
to see all that, to
see it, not verbally, but actually,
through observation, through attention, through care,
through very careful seeing,
that brings an extraordinary quality of intelligence.
After all, intelligence is sensitivity,
to be utterly sensitive.
In seeing, if you call that intelligence the higher self,
or whatever, it has no meaning. You follow?
A. It's as though you are
saying at that instant it is released.
K. Yes, that intelligence comes in observation.
A. Yes.
K. And that intelligence is operating all the time,
if you allow it. Not if
you allow it, if you are seeing.
I mean, I see, I have seen all my life
people who have controlled, people who have denied,
people who have negated, who have sacrificed,
who have controlled, suppressed furiously,
disciplined themselves, tortured themselves.
And I say, for what? For God?
For truth, a mind that
is made tortured, crooked, brutalised,
such a mind can see truth? Certainly not.
You need a completely healthy mind.
A mind that is whole, that is
a mind that is holy in itself.
Otherwise you can't see something holy.
Unless the mind is sacred,
you can't see what is sacred.
And I said, sorry, I won't
touch any of that, it's no meaning.
So I don't know how it has happened,
but I never for a second control myself.
I don't know what it means.
A. And yet amazingly you
know what it is in others.
K. Oh, obviously you can see it.
A. So this is something that
you are able to see without having...
K. Gone through it.
A. Without having gone through it.
Now this to me is profoundly mysterious.
I don't mean in the sense of mystification,
I mean miraculous.
K. No, not necessarily. I'll show you something, sir.
Must I get drunk in order to
find out what it is, with sober?
A. Oh, no, no, no, no.
K. Can't I see a man who
is drunk and say, for God's sake,
see the whole movement of drunkenness,
what lies behind it, what goes
through, see it, and say, finished.
A. But it seems to
me in my listening to you
that you are doing more than just observing,
that someone over there has fallen on his face.
Therefore... K. No, no, no.
A. Right. There is something that is very deep here,
at least to me, that you have said.
Control in the very, very deep
sense is an activity, not a product.
And something that you haven't experienced,
that we would call normally intangible,
is nevertheless acutely present to you.
K. Yes, yes.
A. And I take it that what
you said is that intelligence reveals that,
if intelligence is allowed to reveal it.
K. I think, sir, not allowed,
that's a danger, to allow intelligence to operate.
Which means you have intelligence, then you allow it.
A. Yes, I see the trap of that construction.
Yes, yes, yes, I see what you mean.
Yes, because now we've got an
observer who has got a new gimmick.
K. Yes, that's right.
A. Yes, I see what you mean. Please go on.
K. So, you see, that's
why discipline has a different meaning.
When you understand pleasure,
when you understand its relationship to enjoyment
and to the joy and
happiness and the beauty of happiness,
beauty of joy and so on,
then you understand the utter necessity
of a different kind of discipline that comes naturally.
After all, sir, look at it.
The word discipline in itself means to learn.
To learn. Not to conform.
Not to say, I must
discipline myself to be like that,
or not to be like that.
The word discipline, as we both see, is to learn.
To learn means I must be capable of hearing,
of seeing,
which means the capacity which is not cultivable.
You can cultivate a capacity,
but that's not the same as the act of listening.
I don't know if I'm...
A. Oh, yes, you are. Yes, you are.
Yes, I follow. Very clear, very clear.
K. The capacity to learn demands a certain discipline.
あります
concentrate, I must give my time to it,
I must set aside my efforts
in a certain direction, and all that.
That is, developing a certain capacity needs time.
A. Yes.
K. But perception has nothing to do with time.
You see and act.
As you do when you
see a danger, you act instantly.
You act instantly because you are so conditioned to danger.
That conditioning is not intelligence.
I don't know.
You are just conditioned.
You see a snake and
you recoil, and you run away.
You see a dangerous animal, you run.
That's all self-protective, conditioned responses.
That's very simple.
But perception and action are not conditioned.
كي
نو
We have in the history of the English language
turned that word fear upside
down in terms of its derivation,
because if I remember correctly,
fear comes from the Anglo-Saxon word that means danger.
That means danger. K. K. Of course.
A. Now we have psychologised that word,
and now fear means rather
my emotional response to the danger,
and not what I ought to be doing.
Not aware of the danger of fear. You follow?
S. Yes.
K. That means, sir, look,
ordinary human beings are conditioned, now as they are,
by the culture, by the civilisation they live in.
They accept nationalism, say for instance,
let's take that for example.
They accept nationalism,
and the flag, the nationalism
and all the rest of it.
Nationalism is one of the causes of war.
S. Oh, yes, yes, indubitably, yes.
K. As patriotism and all the rest of it.
Now, we don't see the danger of nationalism,
because we are conditioned to nationalism
as being secure, security.
But we do see our fear of the enemy.
K. Of course.
S. Yes, right.
And contemplating that fear of the enemy dulls
our capacity to deal with the danger.
K. Danger. So, fear, pleasure and discipline.
You follow, sir?
Discipline means to learn.
I am learning about pleasure.
Mind is learning about pleasure.
Learning brings its own order.
S. Its own. K. Its own order.
S. Yes, yes, yes.
That's what I have been calling miracle.
It just asks you to
just jolly well leave it alone.
K. It brings its own order.
And that order says, don't be silly, control it,
it's out, finished.
Now, wait a minute.
I talked to a monk
once, he came to see me.
He had a great many followers,
and he was very well known,
he is still very well known.
And he said, I have taught my disciples
he was very proud of having thousands of disciples.
You follow?
S. Yes, yes.
K. And it seemed rather absurd
for a guru to be proud.
S. He was a success. K. He was a success.
Success means Cadillacs or Rolls Royces,
European and American followers, you follow?
All that circus that goes on.
S. And his gimmick works. K. Gimmick works.
And he was saying, I have arrived
because I have learnt to control my senses,
my body, my thoughts, my desires.
I have held them, as the Gita says,
hold your, you know, something about a reigning,
riding a horse, you know, holding them.
He went on about it for some length.
He said, sir, what at the end of it?
You have controlled, where are
you at the end of it?
He said, what are you asking? I have arrived.
Arrived at what?
I have achieved enlightenment.
Just listen to it, sir.
Follow the sequence of a human being
who has a direction which he calls true,
and to achieve that there are the traditional steps,
the traditional path, the traditional approach,
and he has done it, and
therefore he says, I have got it.
I have got it in my hand.
I know what it is. I said, all right, sir.
He began to be very excited about it
because he wanted to convince me
about being a big man and all that.
I said, I just had to
be very quiet and listen to him.
And he quieted down.
And then I said to him,
we were sitting by the sea,
and I said, do you see that sea, sir?
He said, of course.
Can you hold that water in your hand?
When you hold that water in your hand,
it is no longer the sea.
Q. Right.
K. He couldn't make out.
I said, all right.
And a wind was blowing from the north,
a slight breeze, cool,
and he said, there is the breeze, isn't there?
Can you hold all that?
No.
Can you hold the earth?
So what are you holding?
Words?
You know, sir, he was so angry,
he said, I won't listen to you any more.
You are an evil man.
And walked out.
I was thinking of the absurd irony of that.
All the time he thought
he was holding on to himself,
and he just let go as
he got up and walked away.
K. So you see, sir, that's what I mean.
So, learning about pleasure,
about fear,
really frees you from the tortures of fear
and the pursuit of pleasure.
So there is a sense of real enjoyment in life.
Living then becomes a great joy.
You follow, sir?
It isn't just a monotonous routine,
going to the office, sex and money.
A. I have always thought it's a great misfortune
that in that splendid rhetoric
of our Declaration of Independence
we have that phrase, the pursuit of pleasure.
K. Pursuit of pleasure.
A. Because the child, the bright child,
is reared on that.
K. Oh, rather, sir.
A. And when you are very young
you are not about to turn
around and say everybody is daft.
K. I know.
So from this you see,
discipline in the orthodox sense
has no place
in a mind that is
really wanting to learn about truth.
Not philosophise about truth,
not theorise about truth,
as you say, tie ribbons to it,
learn about it,
learn about pleasure.
It is really out of that learning
comes an extraordinary sense of order,
which we were talking the other day.
The order which comes with the observation
in oneself of pleasure, the order.
And there is pleasure, there is enjoyment.
A marvellous sense of ending each enjoyment
as you live, each moment.
You don't carry over the past enjoyment,
then that becomes pleasure, then it has no meaning.
The repetition of pleasure is monotony, is boredom.
And they are bored in this country, in another country,
because they are fed up with pleasure.
But they want other pleasures in other directions.
And that is why there is
the proliferation of gurus in this country.
Because they all want –
you know, the circus kept going.
So discipline is order.
And discipline means to learn about pleasure,
enjoyment, joy, and the beauty of joy.
When you learn – you follow,
sir? – it is always new.
A. I have just thought – well,
thought is not the right word –
something flashed in the communication
of what you have been pointing to.
If you don't mind, I would rather say
that you have been pointing to
than to use the phrase that you have been saying.
K. Yes, sir, yes.
A. I hope I have understood you correctly here,
because in terms of the communication problem
it seems that there has been a profound confusion
between perception and practice.
I have grasped that.
It is as though we have the idea that perception
is perfected at the end of practice.
K. Practice is routine, is death.
A. We do have that idea. K. I know.
A. Yes. And of course...
K. You see, sir, they have always said
freedom is at the end, not at the beginning.
On the contrary, it is at the beginning.
It is the first step
that counts, not the last step.
So, if we understand this whole question
of fear, pleasure, joy,
the understanding can only come in freedom to observe.
And in the observation, learning and the acting,
they are all at the
same minute, at the same moment.
Not learn, then act.
It is the doing, the seeing,
all taking place at the same time.
That is whole.
A. All these marvellous participles
being in the infinite mode in themselves.
In themselves. Yes.
A little while back it occurred to me that
if we paid attention to our language
as well as to the flowers
and the mountains and the clouds,
the language, not only in terms of individual words,
but words in context,
so that we would refer
then to what we call usage,
would, through perception, intelligence,
disclose themselves completely.
We say, don't we,
that one is pleased, one is joyed,
but if we ask somebody,
if we ask somebody, what have you been doing?
And he said to us, I have been pleasing myself.
We think that was a little odd.
We wouldn't think it strange at all if he said,
well, I have been enjoying myself.
Then we don't mind that.
But we don't pay attention to what we say.
K. That's right, sir.
I mean, as somebody said,
I came back after lunch, after the meal,
and somebody said, have you enjoyed your meal?
And there was a man there who said,
we are not pigs to enjoy.
A. Oh, good Lord!
K. Yes, exactly. Exactly.
I suppose he must feel very righteous
what he denied himself during the meal.
K. Sir, it is a
question of attention, isn't it, really?
A. Yes.
K. Question of attention,
whether you are eating or
whether you are observing pleasure.
The attention,
that is a thing we have
to go into very, very deeply
– I don't know if there is time now –
what it means to attend,
whether we attend to anything at all.
Or it is only a superficial listening,
hearing, seeing, which we call attending.
Or the expression of knowledge in doing.
Attention, I feel, has nothing to do with knowledge
or with action.
In the very attending is action.
One has to go into this
again, question of what is action,
because that is – perhaps
we can do it another day.
A. Yes, I see a relation between
what you have just said about action
and what a few conversations ago we came to
with the word movement. K. Yes.
A. Ongoingness.
And when you were talking about standing
and looking at the tree on the mountain,
I remembered when I was in Rishikesh,
I was staying at one of the ashrams there,
and actually the Vedanta Forest Academy.
And when I got to my quarters,
a monkey came and sat on
the windowsill with her little baby.
And she looked full into my face,
and I looked full into hers,
but I think she looked fuller into mine.
I had that strange feeling that
I was actually a human being,
being… K. Investigated.
A. Investigated, or as the students say today,
being psyched out by this monkey.
And it was a profound shock to me.
K. Talking of monkeys, sir,
I was in Benares, the place I go to usually,
I was doing yoga, exercises, half naked,
and a big monkey with black face and long tail
came and sat on the veranda.
I was doing work, I closed my eyes,
and I looked and there was this big monkey.
He looked at me and I looked at her.
It was a big monkey, sir, they are powerful things.
And it stretched out its hand.
And so I walked up and
held her hand, like that, held it.
And it was rough, but very, very supple,
extraordinary supple, but rough.
And we looked at each other,
and it wanted to come into the room.
I said, look, I am
doing exercises, I have little time,
would you come another day?
I kind of talked to it, come another day,
so it looked at me,
and I went through, went back,
he stayed there for two or three minutes
and gradually went away.
A. Marvelous, just marvellous.
Complete act of attention between you.
K. There was no sense of fear,
it wasn't afraid, I wasn't afraid.
A sense of, you know...
This reminds me of a
story I read about Ramana Maharshi,
how when he was a young man,
he went and lived in a tiger's cave,
and was occupied by the tiger,
and the tiger would come back after the hunt,
in the early hours of
the morning, and sleep with him.
To read that within the environs of our culture,
is... well, it starts... you feel undone.
When you read that, if you think for a moment,
you could allow yourself to believe it.
But in the context of what
we've been saying about the monkeys,
and this marvellous story you told me,
I wish I could have shaken
the hand of that little mother
with her baby.
I wasn't ready to.
K. No, I think it was really...
I don't know, there must have been a communication,
there must have been a sense of friendship, you know,
without any antagonism, without any fear, without any...
it looked at me, you know.
And I think attention is something not to be practised,
not to be cultivated,
go to a school to learn how to be attentive.
That's what they do in this country and other places.
Say, well, I don't know what attention is,
I'm going to learn from somebody who
will tell me how to get it.
Then it's not attention.
A. Speed reading, it's called.
K. Speed, yes.
A. A thousand words a minute.
So, sir, that's why I feel
there is a great sense of care and affection
in being attentive,
which means diligently watching.
That word diligent comes from leisure,
you know, of course, to read.
To read exactly what it is, what is there,
not interpret, not translate it,
not contrive to do something with it,
but to read what is there.
There is an infinite lot to see.
There is tremendous lot to
see in pleasure, as we saw.
Right, sir?
A. Oh, yes.
K. And to read it, you must be watchful, attentive,
diligent, care,
but we are negligent.
You follow? Negligent, we say, yes.
What's wrong with pleasure?
A. There is a colloquial remark in our tongue.
When somebody wishes to secure attention,
they will say, do you read me?
That, of course, has been taken over into technology
into a different aspect.
But quite apart from what someone would be saying
with earphones on in a plane,
just common ordinary practice, sometimes
a person will say that.
K. Sir, what we have done
is really read this whole map
from the beginning of responsibility, relationship,
fear, pleasure, all that we have,
just to observe this extraordinary map of our life.
A. And the beauty of it
is that we have been moving
within the concern for the
question of the transformation of man,
which is not dependent on knowledge or time,
without getting worried about whether
we are getting off the track.
It is happening naturally.
And that, I take it, is
not a surprise to you, of course,
but I am sure that...
I am sure it is shocking in terms of...
K. And that is why also, sir,
it is right to live
with the company of the wise,
be with a man who is really wise,
not this phony people who are wise, but real wisdom,
not bought him in books,
not attending classes where you are taught wisdom.
Wisdom is something that comes with self-knowing.
A. It reminds me of a hymn in the Veda
that talks about the goddess of speech
who never appears except among friends.
K. Yes. A. Marvellous.
Actually that means that unless there is the care,
the affection that you mentioned,
that is continuous, concurrent with attention,
there can be nothing but babble.
There can be verbal babble.
K. Which in the modern world is encouraging, you see.
A. Yes.
K. Again, which means the superficial pleasures,
not enjoyment of... you follow?
Superficial pleasures have become the curse.
And to go behind that is
one of the most difficult things
for people to do.
A. Because it goes faster and faster.
K. That is just it.
A. It goes faster and faster.
That is what is destroying the earth, the air,
everything they are destroying.
There is a place I
go to every year in India,
whether it is a school.
The hills are the oldest hills in the world.
A. What a beautiful thing.
K. Nothing has been changed.
No bulldozers, no new houses.
It is an old place with old hills,
and amongst there is a school
with which I am connected and so on.
And you feel the enormity of time.
The feeling of absolute non-movement,
which is civilisation, which is all
this circus that is going on.
And when you come there you feel this utter quietness,
in which time has not touched it,
time in the sense...
And when you leave it and come to civilisation,
you feel rather lost.
The sense of what is all this about?
Why is there so much noise about nothing?
That's why it is so odd and rather inviting
and a great delight to see everything as is,
including myself, to see what I am.
Not through the eyes of a professor, a psychologist,
a guru, a book, just to see what I am,
and to read what I am,
because all history is in me. You follow?
A. Of course.
There is something immensely beautiful
about what you have said.
Do you think in the next conversation we have
we could talk about the relation
of beauty to what you have said?
K. Yes.
A. Thank you so much.
Thank you.